<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../box.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><section number='About the Authors'>
  <title></title>
  <text>
    <p><b>Daniel Ross: </b> Daniel Ross is a graduate student in the
    mathematics department at the University of Wisconsin--Madison.
    He spends his time thinking about numbers, 18th century English
    poetry, highway interchanges, and the best way to prepare a mango.
    He is an occasional software developer, having written over 17
    lines of code in his life (maybe more, but larger numbers make him
    nervous), as well as sysadmin, frontend designer, and author.
    Despite having written most chapters of this text, he doesn't know
    how to write a bio.  He has never held a baby ostrich.</p>

    <p><b>Karu Sankaralingam: </b> Karu is an associate professor in
    the computer sciences department at the University of
    Wisconsin--Madison, where he also leads the Vertical Research
    Group. His research interests include microarchitecture,
    architecture, and software issues for massively parallel
    computation systems. He is a recipient of the IEEE TCCA Young
    Computer Architecture Award in 2012, an NSF CAREER award in 2009,
    the Emil H Steiger Distinguished Teaching award in 2014, and the
    Letters and Science Philip R. Certain - Gary Sandefur
    Distinguished Faculty Award in 2013 which recognizes outstanding
    teaching by a member of the College of The Letters and Science. He
    earned a PhD from The University of Texas at Austin in December
    2006, and was the lead student architect of the TRIPS chip, a 170
    million transistor chip.</p>
    
    <p><b>Raghuraman Balasubramanian: </b> Raghu is a hardware
    engineer at Google. His interests include microprocessors,
    networking, digital design and computer sciences education. He
    holds masters in Computer Sciences from University of
    Wisconsin--Madison, Electrical Engineering from National
    University of Singapore and Physics from BITS Pilani, India. When
    not working or doing a masters, Raghu can be found playing with
    Arduinos.  His explorations and side-projects during his masters
    work comprised the nucleus around which this course took
    shape.</p>
  </text>
</section>
