<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="box.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<toc>
  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <description>
      <p>Chapter 1 introduces the course as a whole, starting with a
      precise definition of what we mean by the word "computer".  This
      will be a relatively simple notion, and the course will revolve
      around two separate questions:
      <ul><li>How can we program a computer?</li>
      <li>How can we build a computer?</li></ul>

      The first question will be addressed in chapters 2-5, and the
      second in chapters 6-8.</p>
    </description>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Programming</title>
    <description>
      <p>Chapter 2 starts in on the study of programming.  Programming
      occurs in two steps: When we come up against a problem, the
      first step is to describe a precise sequence of steps that will
      solve it.  Such a set of steps, written in English (or human
      language of choice) is called an algorithm, and is the focus of
      section 2.2.  </p>

      <p>Once we have an algorithm, the second step is to rewrite that
      algorithm not in human language, but in a
      computer-understandable language.  This will be the program.  In
      section 2.3, we introduce a particular programming language--a
      simplified version of Python--to illustrate this process.  </p>
    </description>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Advanced Programming</title>
    <description>
      <p>In chapter 2, we learned a simple subset of the Python
      programming language.  Its simplicity made it easier to explain,
      but hard to use for any complicated or interesting tasks.
      Chapter 3 is devoted to expanding our knowledge of Python so we
      can work toward programs that actually behave like software as
      we know it in the real world.  </p>
    </description>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Numbers in Computer Science</title>
    <description>
      <p>Chapter 4 is a brief digression: As we descend to the level
      of the computer hardware, we are going to need a new language to
      talk about numbers as a computer understands them.  This is
      accomplished by the binary representation of numbers, which is
      the focus of chapter 4.</p>
    </description>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>ISA</title>
    <description>
      <p>In chapters 2 and 3, we learned our first programming language.
      However this language is not something that a computer
      understands itself.  Rather, the computer understands a much
      more basic language, called the ISA, and our programs from
      chapters 2 and 3 were being secretly translated to this basic
      language before being run by the computer.  </p>

      <p>To truly understand what a computer does under the hood, we
      need to learn to work with the ISA directly.  This happens in
      two parts: We learn what the main components inside the computer
      are (that is, the computer's "architecture"), and then we learn
      what instructions the computer itself natively understands for
      manipulating these components (that is, the computer's
      "instruction set").</p>
    </description>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Encodings and the ISA</title>
    <description>
      <p>Chapter 5 is another brief but fun digression to address the
      question of, now that we know that the computer deals in
      numbers, how is it that we can manipulate things like text and
      images using computers as well?  The answer is that everything
      that a computer with, from text to images to the ISA
      instructions themselves, must actually be numbers behind the
      scenes.  The schemes by which numbers are made to correspond to
      text or to graphical data or to instructions are called
      encodings, and we explore several different types of encoding in
      this chapter.</p>
    </description>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Microarchitecture</title>
    <description>
      <p>Chapter 7 resumes the `How to build a computer' thread by
      taking the major tasks that the various ISA instructions need to
      be able to accomplish, imagining we have some black-box circuit
      components that perform these tasks, and examining how these
      large-scale components can be connected to create an actual
      computer.  </p>
    </description>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Digital Logic and Transistors</title>
    <description>
      <p>Finally, now that we know that to build a computer, all that
      remains is to build the components we hooked up in the previous
      chapter, we examine the building blocks of digital circuits:
      Logic gates and, ultimately, transistors.  </p>
    </description>
  </chapter>
</toc>
