<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><quest name="HW 5" id="5">

<q type="avr" id="Problem 11">
  <program></program>
  <text>Write assembly code to configure the complete PORT D as an
  output port and write 134 on this port. <b>Annotate your code with
  comments for full credit.</b>  </text>
</q>

<q type="avr" id="Problem 12">
  <program></program>
  <text>
    Using the stack, write a simple assembly language function labeled
    myfunction that compares the values in the top two entries of the
    stack and prints the higher number to the output LED. If they are
    equal, print either value.
	
<p>Initialize your stack to RAM location 3000. Place values 4 and 3
into registers, and then call this function. <b>Annotate your code
with comments for full credit.</b></p>

  </text>
</q>

<q type="avr" id="Problem 13">
  <program></program>
  <text>
Convert the following Python code into assembly language. Assume x is
stored in r16, y in r17, and z in r18, and a in r19. You may store
values in other registers if necessary. <b>Annotate your code with
comments for full credit.</b>

<pre>x = 2
y = 1
z = x + y
if(z >= 2):
   a = 1
else:
   a = 2</pre>
  </text>
</q>

<q type="avr" id="Problem 14">
  <program></program>
  <text>Repeat Homework 2 Question 11, but this time use assembly
  language instead of Python.  A hard coded solution will result in 0
  points (see the homework PDF for examples of this).  Because 377
  does not fit in 8 bits, the last Fibonacci number may be outputted
  as 121.  <b>Annotate your code with comments for full credit.  </b>
  </text>
</q>

<q type="avr" id="Problem 15">
  <program></program>
  <text>Repeat Homework 2 Question 12, but this time use assembly
  language instead of Python, and go from 32 to 50 instead.
  <b>Annotate your code with comments for full credit.</b> <p>Hints:
  <ol>
    <li>You may have to write your own multiply by doing multiple adds.</li>
    <li>You may have to write your own divide by using a quotient counter,
    and subtracting the divisor from the dividend while the dividend is
    greater than the divisor. </li>
  </ol>
  </p>

  </text>
</q>
</quest>
