<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><?xml-stylesheet href="box.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><section number='4A'>
<title>Advanced ISA and Assembly Language</title>
<section><title>Advanced ISA Features</title>

<section><title>Advanced addressing modes</title>
<summary>AVR has instructions for easily reading or writing a set of
successive of addresses in RAM.</summary>

<text>
<p>Earlier we discussed instructions for reading from and storing to
address X.  But suppose we have 20 values in RAM, starting at address
500, and we want to do something to each of them.  

<code>500 = 244 + 256*1</code>

So to read the first slot in this sequence, we set r26 = 244 and r27 =
1: 

<code>ldi r26, 244
ldi r27, 1
ld r0, X
...[Do stuff with the value in r0 that we just read from RAM]</code>
</p>

<p>The next slot will be at 501, so since 

<code>501 = 245 + 256*1</code>

we need can just increment r26 and leave r27 alone: 

<code>ldi r26, 244
ldi r27, 1
ld r0, X
...[Do stuff with the value in r0 that we just read from RAM slot 500]
inc r26
ld r0, X
...[Do stuff with the value in r0 that we just read from RAM slot 501]
</code>

</p>

<p>We can do this several more times without issue, but around slot
511 we will start to have a problem, since

<code>511 = 255 + 256*1</code>

So r26 will be 255, and incrementing it will cause an overflow, making
it 0.  Then we'll be reading from slot 0 + 256*1 = 256, rather than
slot 512.  </p>

<p>So this is exactly the problem we faced before of incrementing a
combined number.  So to fix this, we could also add C to r27 as we
discussed in the previous section.  However, it turns out that this
operation of reading a sequence of values in memory is common enough
that there is a modified version of the 'read from X' instruction
which again reads from X, but then increments X correctly after it
does so.  </p>

<p>This instruction is again called ld, and its first operand is again
a register in which to store the value read from RAM, but for its
second operand we write X+, telling it to increment X after reading
the value.  </p>

<p>With this instruction, our code becomes: 
<code>ldi r26, 244
ldi r27, 1
ld r0, X+
...[Do stuff with the value in r0 that we just read from RAM slot 500]
ld r0, X+
...[Do stuff with the value in r0 that we just read from RAM slot 501]
ld r0, X+
...[Do stuff with the value in r0 that we just read from RAM slot 502]
...
</code>

and the ld __, X+ instruction takes care of incrementing X carefully,
exactly as we learned to do by hand in the previous section.</p>

<p>There is an analogous 'st X+, register' instruction that stores to
address X and then increments X afterward.  Further, because going
backwards through memory is also a reasonably common operation, there
are also instructions for decrementing X before reading or storing.
These are all described in the table below: </p>

<table class='ISA_table'><tr>
<td>Instruction</td>
<td>Description</td>
<td>Operand 1</td>
<td>Operand 2</td>
<td>Effect on operands</td>
<td>Effect on specials</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><pre>ld</pre></td>
<td>Load from RAM and increment address</td>
<td><pre>reg</pre></td>
<td><pre>X+</pre></td>
<td><pre>op1 = RAM[r26 + 256*r27]
X = X + 1</pre></td>
<td><pre>pc: increment
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><pre>st</pre></td>
<td>Store to RAM and increment address</td>
<td><pre>X+</pre></td>
<td><pre>reg</pre></td>
<td><pre>RAM[r26 + 256*r27] = op2
X = X + 1</pre></td>
<td><pre>pc: increment
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr><tr>
<td><pre>ld</pre></td>
<td>Decrement address and load from RAM</td>
<td><pre>reg</pre></td>
<td><pre>-X</pre></td>
<td><pre>X = X - 1
op1 = RAM[r26 + 256*r27]</pre></td>
<td><pre>pc: increment
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><pre>st</pre></td>
<td>Decrement address and store to RAM</td>
<td><pre>-X</pre></td>
<td><pre>reg</pre></td>
<td><pre>X = X - 1
RAM[r26 + 256*r27] = op2</pre></td>
<td><pre>pc: increment
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr>
</table>
</text></section>

<section><title>The stack</title>
<summary>AVR also provides a mechanism for quickly saving/restoring
the values of registers by means of the stack.  The stack is a region
in RAM that can be accessed by special instructions that make it
convenient to store a bunch of register values there and later restore
those values to the actual registers.  </summary>
<text>
<p>AVR provides us with 32 general-purpose registers for computation
and whatever else we need.  In many cases, this is plenty, but
sometimes we want to quickly save off a register value or two and
restore them later.  </p>

<p>There are instructions that do exactly this, called push and pop,
both of which take just one register for an operand.  Before we
discuss what these actually do in terms of the architecture, we will
describe how to think about them: </p>

<p>When you push a register, e.g.

<code>push r0</code>

This will save the value in r0 somewhere.  If you then do 

<code>pop r1</code>

this will take stored that value and put it in r1.  </p>

<p>If we instead push multiple registers, like: 

<code>push r0
push r1
push r0
push r5</code>

then this saves the values of those registers in that order.  The pop
instruction then recovers the values we stored with push in reverse
order.  If we do 

<code>pop r10
pop r11
pop r12
pop r13</code>

then the first thing that gets popped into r10 is the value we stored
from r5.  Then when we pop into r11, this gets the value that was
pushed from r0.  Then r12 gets the value that was pushed from r1.
Then r13 gets the value from r0.</p>

<p>This behaviour is often described as a <b>stack</b>, because
'pushing' a value is like placing that value on the top of a stack.
Then 'popping', is like taking the top value off the stack.  </p>

<figure><description>The register file is represented by a row of
boxes with whatever values in them.  We represent the stack by a stack
of numbers, maybe written on blocks or something (something stackable,
or otherwise not a row/column of boxes so that it doesn't get mistaken
for a memory) and show its evolution (as well as that of the register
file) through a sequence of push and pop
operations.</description><caption></caption></figure>

<p>This is a helpful mental picture to have when using the stack, but
it is only that.  The architectural reality behind this conceptual
idea of the stack is the following: 

<def term='stack pointer'><def term='sp'>There is a RAM address called
the <b>stack pointer</b>--often called <b>sp</b>.</def></def> When we
push a register, its value gets written to RAM at the address sp, and
then sp gets decremented by 1.  When you pop a register, the
stack pointer gets incremented by 1 and then the register receives the
value in RAM at the address sp.  </p>

<figure><description>The above figure, now showing the stack in RAM
and the sp instead of the representative stack, and showing the
evolution of this through the same sequence of
pushes/pops.</description><caption></caption></figure>

<p>So push and pop behave as in the mental model, using a region in
RAM to store the values.  But where, in turn, is this mysterious stack
pointer stored?  As with many mysterious things, this is actually
stored using the I/O registers.  Since sp is an address in RAM, it has
to be a combined number from two registers, like X.  In this case, it
is made up of I/O registers 61 and 62 as:

<code>sp = IO[61] + 256*IO[62]</code>

In particular, if we are going to use push and pop instructions, we
have to first set the sp to some sensible place in RAM where it
doesn't get in the way of anything else we do in RAM.  For example,
maybe we decide to set it to 5000 to keep it out of the way.  Since 

<code>5000 = 12*256 + 136</code>

we need to set IO[61] to 136 and IO[62] to 12.  We can do this using
the 'out' instruction to write to the I/O registers:

<code>ldi r31, 136
out 61, r31
ldi r31, 12
out 62, r31</code>

Now the stack is set up, and the first push will write to address 5000
in RAM, the next push will write to address 4999, etc.  </p>

<table class='ISA_table'><tr>
<td>Instruction</td>
<td>Description</td>
<td>Operand 1</td>
<td>Operand 2</td>
<td>Effect on operands</td>
<td>Effect on specials</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><pre>push</pre></td>
<td>Push register to stack</td>
<td><pre>reg</pre></td>
<td><pre>none</pre></td>
<td><pre>RAM[sp] = op1
sp = sp - 1</pre></td>
<td><pre>pc: increment
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><pre>pop</pre></td>
<td>Pop register off stack</td>
<td><pre>reg</pre></td>
<td><pre>none</pre></td>
<td><pre>sp = sp + 1
op1 = RAM[sp]</pre></td>
<td><pre>pc: increment
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr>
</table>
</text></section>

<section><title>Functions</title>
<summary>The construction of a function in Python was a useful way to
reuse a chunk of code in several places without just copying it.  The
AVR ISA has support for this behaviour in the form of its rcall and
ret instructions.  </summary>
<text>
<p>In Python, if we ever wrote a piece of code that we want to reuse
elsewhere, we could package it up as a function and then call it from
multiple places elsewhere in our code.  In the ISA, we have already
seen code that would be useful to treat this way: Our code for
outputting a number (say, the contents of r30): 

<code>ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30</code>

If we end up wanting to output more than one thing in our program,
we'll have this snippet of code appearing everywhere, so if we could
reuse it more effeciently that would be excellent.  However, it turns
out that having a chunk of code that we can reuse in this way is
tricky: The main challenge comes from the fact that we have to be able
to jump to this chunk of code from anywhere, run the code, and then
have the code jump back to wherever it was called from.  </p>

<p>The AVR ISA comes with two instructions--called rcall and
ret--which together accomplish this by using the stack.  rcall takes a
single operand, which is a value in the range -64-63.  It pushes onto
the stack the value pc + 1, and then adds the operand + 1 to the
pc--effectively jumping to some other piece of code.  So this has put
us in another section of our code and has saved the address of the
instruction after the rcall--i.e. the instruction that we want to
return to after we finish our chunk of code!</p>

<p>To actually use this stored value to return to where we called the
code, we use the ret instruction, which takes no operands and very
simply pops the pc off the stack.  </p>

<table class='ISA_table'><tr>
<td>Instruction</td>
<td>Description</td>
<td>Operand 1</td>
<td>Operand 2</td>
<td>Effect on operands</td>
<td>Effect on specials</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><pre>rcall</pre></td>
<td>Call relative address</td>
<td><pre>value -64-63</pre></td>
<td><pre>none</pre></td>
<td><pre>RAM[sp] = pc
sp = sp - 1</pre></td>
<td><pre>pc = pc + op1
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><pre>ret</pre></td>
<td>Return from most recent call</td>
<td><pre>none</pre></td>
<td><pre>none</pre></td>
<td><pre></pre></td>
<td><pre>sp = sp + 1
pc = RAM[sp]
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>For example, we can now try to write code that reuses our above
output code.  Let us consider writing code that first outputs the
number 13, then multiplies it by 8 and outputs that.  We can start
with the outline: 

<code>ldi r30, 13
[call to output code to output r30]
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
[call to output code to output r30]
</code>

We need to put our output code somewhere, so maybe we'll put it at the
beginning: 

<code>ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30
ldi r30, 13
[call to output code to output r30]
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
[call to output code to output r30]
</code>

But now when we first run this program, our output code will be run
first, and then our interesting code will be run.  That's no good.  We
could put it at the end, but then that just moves the problem to the
end of the program, where the output code will be run an extra time
once everything else is finished.  To resolve this, we make the first
instruction an rjmp which skips over the output code to the first line
of our computation code: 

<code>rjmp 3
ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30
ldi r30, 13
[call to output code to output r30]
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
[call to output code to output r30]
</code>

Now we can fill in the call lines: the first one is making a call 4
instructions back, so it will be rcall -5, and the second call needs
to call the code 8 instructions back, so it will be rcall -9: 

<code>rjmp 3
ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30
ldi r30, 13
rcall -5
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
rcall -9
</code>

But this is no good still--once we rcall -5, we jump back to the line 

<code>ldi 255, r31</code>

and essentially start over.  Rather, we want our output code to use
the ret instruction once it finishes: 

<code>rjmp 4
ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30
ret
ldi r30, 13
rcall -6
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
rcall -10
</code>

(Note we've had to shift all the rcall and rjmp operands.)</p>

<p>There is another issue: rcall is using the stack, but we don't
actually know at this point that sp is an address that makes sense,
since we never set it up.  So we do this as the first thing: 

<code>ldi r31, 136
out 61, r31
ldi r31, 12
out 62, r31
rjmp 4
ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30
ret
ldi r30, 13
rcall -6
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
add r30, r30
rcall -10
</code>

And now, finally, we've got things set up so that we can reuse the
outputting code as we'd hoped.</p>

<p>There were quite a few pitfalls in getting this set up, so we
record for future reference our code-reuse checklist: 

<ul>
  <li>Ensure that the sp is set to something sensible</li>
  <li>Place the reuseable somewhere where it won't get executed,
  e.g. by placing it at the beginning and jumping over it.</li>
  <li>Ensure the reuseable code ends with a ret instruction</li>
  <li>Call the code using rcall with an operand that shifts you to the
  start of the reuseable code, being careful to update these offsets
  if you change any intervening code.</li>
</ul></p>

<p><b>Caller vs. callee-saved registers: </b></p>

<p>There is one further issue that doesn't actually cause a problem in
the above example, but can easily become a problem in more complicated
examples, namely that the output code trashes the r31 register.
Specifically, it fills it with a value that it uses for its own
purposes, overwriting whatever value was in it before.  </p>

<p>To see this in action, suppose instead of multiplying r30 by 8, we
wanted to add the number 41 to it two times, output r30, and then add
41 to it three more times and output the result of that:

<code>ldi r31, 136
out 61, r31
ldi r31, 12
out 62, r31
rjmp 4
ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30
ret
ldi r30, 13
rcall -6
ldi r31, 41
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
rcall -10
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
rcall -14
</code>

In this example, we use r31 to hold our value of 41 that we are adding
to r30.  But after the line 

<code>rcall -10</code>

we continue adding r31 to r30, expecting that r31 still has the value
41, oblivious to the fact that our output code overwrites r31 with the
value 255!  </p>

<p>There are two remedies--we can make our output code save the
previous value of r31 using the stack, and then restore it before it
returns: </p>

<code>ldi r31, 136
out 61, r31
ldi r31, 12
out 62, r31
rjmp 6
push r31
ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30
pop r31
ret
ldi r30, 13
rcall -8
ldi r31, 41
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
rcall -12
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
rcall -16
</code>

<p>(Note again the need to adjust the operands to the jumps and
calls.)</p>

<p><def term='callee-saved'>In this case, r31 is being saved by the
function we're calling, so it is referred to as a <b>callee-saved
register</b>.</def> Another option would be that before we call the
code, we note that it will trash r31 and so we save it onto the stack
before calling and then restore it after the code returns: 

<code>ldi r31, 136
out 61, r31
ldi r31, 12
out 62, r31
rjmp 4
ldi 255, r31
out 26, r31
out 27, r30
ret
ldi r30, 13
rcall -6
ldi r31, 41
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
push r31
rcall -11
pop r31
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
add r30, r31
rcall -16
</code>

<def term='caller-saved'>In this case, the output code will happily
trash r31, and it is the responsibility of any code that calls it to
save its value.  In this case, the register is known as a
<b>caller-saved register</b>.</def>

</p>

<p><b>Aside--Abusing rcall: </b>You'll have noted that most of our
operations thus far only act on general-purpose registers.  However if
we really wanted, we could make them act on sreg or sp by reading
these from the appropriate I/O registers into the general-purpose
registers, computing with these general-purpose registers, and then
writing the results back to the relevant I/O registers.  However none
of our instructions can take pc as an operand, and pc doesn't actually
live in the I/O register file either.  </p>

<p>So if we're merrily going through a program and for whatever reason
we want to get the current pc in a register, there is not an
instruction we can use that does this.  However, we can accomplish it
in several instructions with a slight abuse of rcall: note that rcall
places the address after the current pc on the stack.  And we have an
instruction that reads a value off the stack into a register--namely
pop.  So we can do:

<code>rcall 1
pop r0</code>

and this will put the stored pc into register r0!  Note that this
stored pc is the address of the pop instruction in program memory, but
we can subsequently adjust r0 with arithmetic operations to get r0 to
be the address of whatever instruction we're actually interested in.
</p>

</text></section>


<section><title>Further ISA features</title>
<text>
<p>We have described most of the major families of instructions in the
AVR ISA, but there are a very large number of instructions defined as
part of the ISA beyond what we've mentioned.  Some of these perform
functions that we have not mentioned, such as reading an actual
encoded instruction from the program memory into a register.  Others
perform functions that we can perform by using the instructions
described here, but which are packaged into a single extra instruction
for convenience.  An example of such an instruction that is not
strictly necessary is cp.  We note that cp sets the sreg flags in
exactly the same way as sub, so everywhere we used cp, we could have
used sub instead.  The inconvenience is that sub also modifies one of
its operands, and if we're just comparing two numbers we often don't
want this comparison to also modify one of them.  So we can do
literally the same thing as 

<code>cp r10, r11</code>

by saving off the value (r10) that will get modified by sub and then
restoring it after: 

<code>push r10
sub r10, r11
pop r10</code></p>

<p>Not all of these 'convenient but not strictly necessary'
instructions are available on all models of AVR computer--cheaper
chips may have a more barebones set of available instructions.  For a
complete list of all instructions, and a breakdown of which are
available on which models of AVR microprocessor, refer to [Wikipedia?
Some Atmel document?]</p>
</text>
</section>
</section>

<section><title>Assembly language</title>
<summary>Assembly language is the programming language that one often
uses to write code in the ISA.  It is easy to convert from assembly to
nothing but pure ISA instructions--a job that is done by an
'assembler'--but assembly has features that make it easier to use than
the ISA itself.</summary>
<text>
<p>Writing useful code using the ISA can be a pain.  At one level, it
is going to be difficult no matter what, since each instruction only
performs one small operation at a time, so anything complicated will
take a large number of instructions.  At the same time, there are some
things that are sufficiently difficult that a very small layer was
created to put on top of the ISA, namely assembly language.  </p>

<p><def term='assembly langauge'><b>Assembly language </b> is a
programming language whose syntax mostly consists of ISA instructions,
but which has a few additional features to ameliorate some of the more
painful tasks when programming in the ISA directly.  </def> The tasks
of this sort that we shall address specifically are the following:

<ul>
<li><b>Specifying offsets for relative jumps and branches: </b>Recall our
example above in listing ???.  We have multiple rcalls to a particular
place in the code, but because rcall requires an offset, we have to
recompute each offset for each individual rcall.  Further, if we ever
want to add anything to the middle of the program, we have to
recalculate all the offsets.  Assembly language includes a mechanism
for jumping to a specific location that will, in effect, compute all
these offsets for us.  This mechanism is called labels.</li>
<li><b>Initialising RAM with specified data: </b>Currently, if we want a
large amount of data stored in RAM, then since the only way of storing
data we have is with the st instructions, we will have to do one st
instrucion for each number we want stored.  This can get tedious if we
have hundreds of things to store, so assembly provides a mechanism to
pre-populate RAM at specified locations with whatever values are
desired.</li>
<li><b>Strings: </b>We haven't yet discussed how Python's strings can
be realised in the ISA.  This discussion will largely be deferred to
the next chapter, but for now we mention that there is some way to
correspond letters in a string to numbers 0-255.  So storing a string
would involve looking up which letters correspond to which numbers and
using st instructions to store the appropriate sequence of numbers.
Assembly includes syntax to let us simply type the desired string and
have the assembler convert this to numbers for storage. </li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>Now, we're trying to program the computer.  What this means is
getting certain numbers corresponding to our desired instructions into
the program memory of the computer.  <def term='assembler'>When we
write a program in assembly language, a program called an
<b>assembler</b> will convert this into numbers for storage into the
program memory.</def> However, assembly language not only allows you
to populate program memory with numbers corresponding to instructions,
but also allows you to pre-populate RAM with numbers if desired.</p>

<p>As mentioned, assembly language is a programming language, so just
as we explained the Python programming language in terms of its
syntax--what constructions are legal, and its semantics--what the
constructions mean, we can do this with assembly.  Further, since all
an assembly language program is meant to do is turn into certain
numbers that will go into program memory and certain other numbers
that go into RAM, describing the semantics of an element of assembly
language is as easy as explaining what numbers it corresponds to and
where in memory those numbers are stored.  </p>


	<table>
	  <tr>
	    <td>Language element</td>
	    <td>Syntax</td>
	    <td>Semantics</td>
	    <td>Examples</td>
	  </tr>
	  
	  <tr>
	    <td>Line</td>
	    <td>Either an <i>ISA operation</i>, a <i>label</i>,
	    or an <i>assembler directive</i>.</td>
	    <td>A line is the basic unit of assemvly language code.
	    Each line in an assembly program is run in sequence.</td>
	    <td>
</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>ISA operation</td>
	    <td>An ISA operation can be any of the above operations we
	    described.  The added feature is that is that in place of
	    an operand that represents an offset, you may use a label
	    name, and in place of a number you may use a character</td>
	    <td>Performs the specified ISA operation</td>
	    <td>
	      <pre>ldi r31, 51</pre><br />
	      <pre>cpi r14, 'A'</pre><br />
	      <pre>breq -17</pre><br />
	      <pre>rjmp hello</pre><br />
	    </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>Label</td>
	    <td><pre><i>label_name</i>:</pre></td>
	    <td>Marks this offset in the program as being named by the
	    given label name</td>
	    <td>
	      <pre>hello: </pre><br />
	      <pre>this_is_a_label: </pre><br />
	    </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>Assembler directive</td>
	    <td>Either a <i>byte directive</i>, or a <i>string
	    directive</i></td>
	    <td>
	      <pre>.byte 101</pre>
	      <pre>.byte 121,87,0,33</pre>
	      <pre>.string "hello"</pre>
	    </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>Label name</td>
	    <td>Any combination of letters, numbers, and underscores,
	    except that a variable name cannot begin with a number or
	    be a name that Python already treats as special (e.g. if,
	    while, else--for a complete list, see the next section)</td>
	    <td>Specifies the name of a variable.</td>
	    <td><pre>helo
abc1DEF0__0GHIJ</pre><br /><br />

Non-examples: 

<pre>2hello
7
true
my name</pre></td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>Character</td>
	    <td>Any single character from the keyboard enclosed in
	    single quotes</td>
	    <td>Stands in for a number that represents that character
	    (see ASCII in the next chapter).  </td>
	    <td>
	      <pre>'h'</pre>
	      <pre>'A'</pre>
	      <pre>'%'</pre>
	      <pre>' '</pre>
	    </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>String</td>
	    <td>Any sequence of characters (except a single-quote)
	    enclosed in double-quotes.</td>
	    <td>Strings provide a method to store and manipulate
	    text.  </td>
	    <td>
<pre>&quot;Hello world!&quot;
&quot;'That is beautiful', he said&quot;</pre>
	    </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>byte directive</td>
	    <td><pre>.byte <i>list of bytes</i></pre></td>
	    <td>Instructs that these bytes should be inserted into the
	    program at this point.  Note that a byte can either by a
	    number 0-255 or a character</td>
	    <td>
	      <pre>.byte 42</pre>
	      <pre>.byte 0, 0, 0, 0, 0</pre>
	      <pre>.byte 123, 'A', 1</pre>
	    </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>string directive</td>
	    <td>
	      <pre>.ascii <i>string</i></pre>
	    </td>
	    <td>Translates each character in the string into a byte
	    and inserts those bytes into the program at the location
	    of the string directive in order.</td>
	    <td></td>
	  </tr>
	</table>

	<p>As with Python, assembly language has in fact many features
	beyond those explained here, but they are much less powerful
	than the extra features of Python, and from this book we shall
	elide them entirely.</p>
</text>

<section><title>ISA Operations</title>
<text>
  <p>We have already discussed in detail the syntax and semantics of
  the various ISA operations.  The only thing new in assembly language
  is the ability to replace certain operands with characters or
  labels.  Specifically:
  <ul>
    <li><p>Any operand designated above as an 'offset' can be replaced
    with the name of a label.  This covers the operands to rjmp,
    rcall, and all the branch instructions.  The assembler will then
    compute the offset in the program between the jump/branch
    instruction and the location in the code where the label appears
    and will substitute that offset as the actual operand.  </p>

    <p>For example, take the program:

    <code>hello:
ldi r31,0
cpi r31,8
breq stuff
inc r31
rjmp hello
stuff:
dec r31
cpi r31,8
breq stuff</code>

The label 'stuff' appears two instructions after the first 'breq
stuff' instruction, so the assembler replaces the first 'breq stuff'
with 'breq 2'.  On the other hand, the stuff label appears three
instructions before the second 'breq stuff', so this is replaced with
'breq -3'.  Likewise, 'rjmp hello' gets replaced by 'rjmp -5'.  So
the above program is equivalent to: 


<code>ldi r31,0
cpi r31,8
breq 2
inc r31
rjmp -5
dec r31
cpi r31,8
breq -3</code>

Of course, writing the program using labels means we don't have to
adjust all the offsets of our jumps and branches if we change the
program a little, so labels do indeed solve that problem.
    </p>
    </li>
    <li>Any character corresponds to a byte in a standard way.  So
    with just the naive ISA operations, we could already do string
    manipulation by taking any string we wanted to use, figuring out
    which bytes its characters corresponded to, and using those
    numbers in place of the actual string.  This would make the
    purpose of a program rather hard to divine, however.  Imagine:
<code>ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 72
out 27, r30
ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 105
out 27, r30</code>

    We know from earlier that this is outputting the numbers 72 and
    105, but these numbers turn out to correspond to the characters
    'H' and 'i', respectively.  So this is outputting the text 'Hi',
    and we can make this more evident by replacing the numbers with
    the characters they correspond to:  
<code>ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 'H'
out 27, r30
ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 'i'
out 27, r30</code>

    The assembler will turn this into the earlier program anyway,
    since ldi of course requires a number as its second operand, but
    we are free to use characters when they are more convenient than
    the raw numbers and let the assembler take care of the conversion.
    </li>
  </ul>
  </p>

  <p>As we mentioned, the assembler's job is to put numbers into
  program memory corresponding to the specified instructions.  We've
  seen how to specify ISA operations, even using labels and characters
  when convenient, but have not discussed the conversion of ISA
  operations into numbers.  This will be the topic of the next
  chapter, and for now all we mention is that there is some
  correspondence.  For example, the instruction

  <code>ori r22,0x58</code>

  corresponds to the number 26725.  
  </p>
  
</text></section>

<section><title>Labels</title>
<text>
  <p>Labels are lines that look like:

  <code><i>label_name</i>: </code>

  Where a label name can be exactly what a variable name in Python
  could be: Anything containing only letters, numbers, or underscores,
  except it cannot start with a number.</p>
  
  <p>Labels are used to mark a place in the programto refer to in
  actual instructions, as in the examples of the previous section.
  They do not themselves constitute actual instructions.  For example,
  the two programs below are identical in terms of the instructions
  that will be stored in program memory: 

  <code>ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 'H'
out 27, r30
ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 'i'
out 27, r30</code>


<code>hello:
ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 'H'
some_label: 
out 27, r30
ldi r30, 255
babel: 
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 'i'
out 27, r30</code>

  </p>
</text></section>

<section><title>Assembler directives</title>
<text>

<p>We will discuss only two kinds of assembler directives here, which
will serve the single purpose of helping us pre-populate RAM with
data.  We should note that this task is not an easy one--</p>

<!-- <p><b>Data directive: </b></p> -->

<!-- <p>Every line of an assembly program gets translated into numbers: ISA -->
<!-- operations get translated to numbers of width 16 according to the -->
<!-- encoding, and label lines get translated to nothing (though their -->
<!-- location in the program is used to help translate other ISA operations -->
<!-- that refer to them), and all these numbers get stored into program -->
<!-- memory.  Until, that is, the program reaches the data directive.  </p> -->

<!-- <p><def term='data directive'>The <b>data directive</b> is a line in -->
<!-- an assembly program that just contains the content:  -->

<!-- <pre>.data</pre> -->

<!-- It can show up at most once per program, and every line of the program -->
<!-- that appears before this directive, when it gets translated into a -->
<!-- number, gets stored in program memory.  Every line of the program -->
<!-- following the data directive, when translated into a number, will -->
<!-- be placed into RAM instead.  </def></p> -->

<!-- <p>Of course, then we have to ask: What can we put after the data -->
<!-- directive?  All the valid lines of assembly language we know about -->
<!-- thus far are ISA operations, labels, and the data directive.  The only -->
<!-- one of those that actually corresponds to numbers, are ISA -->
<!-- operations.  For example, the ISA operation -->

<!-- <pre>ldi r30, 255</pre> -->

<!-- corresponds to the two numbers: -->

<!-- <pre>239, 239</pre> -->

<!-- So if we want two consecutive 239's stored into RAM, we can do: -->

<!-- <pre>.data -->
<!-- ldi r30, 255</pre> -->

<!-- However this is hard: What if we want only one 239?  Or if we want a -->
<!-- 238 instead?  Do we have to go find an instruction whose encoding -->
<!-- includes the number 238?  Thankfully the answer is 'no', and there is -->
<!-- a way of specifying precisely what numbers you want without having to -->
<!-- reference the ISA's encoding.  This is the job of the byte directive. -->
<!-- </p> -->

<p><b>Byte directives</b></p>

<p><def term='byte directive'>A <b>byte directive</b> looks like:

<code>.byte 12,189,200,0,0</code>

It will write the sequence of bytes (separated by commas) in the list
into program memory verbatim.  </def></p>

<p>For a example: 

<code>.byte 12,56,121,0,0,0,0
.byte 78
.byte 255,'A'</code>

are all valid byte directives--the last because, as we discussed, 'A'
is a valid way to speicfy the byte that encodes the character 'A',
namely 65.</p>

<p>Since everything that gets written to program memory anyway is
numbers, we can write our whole program with byte directives by
knowing what numbers our instructions would be translated into.  For
example, the program

<code>ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30, 'i'
out 27, r30</code>

would be turned into the numbers

<code>61423,48106,59113,48107</code>

Translating these into bytes, e.g. 61423 = 239*256+239, we find that
this program is equivalent to:

<code>.byte 239,239,234,187,233,230,235,187</code>

TODO: check endianness issues.
</p>

<p>In general, however, we don't write programs using the byte
directive.  Instead, we use the byte directive to include data that we
want to reference in our program.  For example, if we want to sun the
first 10 Fibonacci numbers, we could write some code to compute these,
or we could just place them into our program with a byte directive:

<code>.byte 1,1,2,3,5,8,13,21,35,56</code></p>

<p>Another sort of data that we often want to manipulate is string
data.  Using the byte directive, we can store the string 'Hello
World!' in our program like:

<code>.byte 'H','e','l','l','o',' ','W','o','r','l','d','!'</code></p>

<p><b>String directives</b></p>

<p>That last example for including strings may have looked a little
inconvenient, so assembly language provides a second directive that
makes this easier: the <b>string directive</b>.

<def term='string directive'>The string directive looks like:

<code>.ascii <i>string</i></code>

where a string is the same as it was in our description of Python--any
sequence of characters enclosed in double quotes, where newlines,
tabs, and double-quotes inside the string are all represented with
escape sequences.</def></p>

<p>For example, we can recover the 'Hello World!' example with the
string directive simply thus:

<code>.asciz &quot;Hello World!&quot;</code></p>

<p><b>Getting data into RAM</b></p>

<p>The byte and string directives allow us to put data into program
memory, but you notice that all our storage instructions were about
loading from and storing to registers and to RAM--never to the program
memory.  So how can this newfound ability to store bytes in the
program memory help us?  It turns out there is one further instruction
in the ISA we did not mention, which loads a single byte from program
memory into a register.  It is called 'lpm' (for 'load from program
memory') and, other than the fact that it loads from program memory
instead of RAM, it behaves the same as the load instruction that
incremented Z: </p>

<table class='ISA_table'><tr>
<td>Instruction</td>
<td>Description</td>
<td>Operand 1</td>
<td>Operand 2</td>
<td>Effect on operands</td>
<td>Effect on specials</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><pre>adc</pre></td>
<td>Add with carry</td>
<td><pre>reg</pre></td>
<td><pre>Z+</pre></td>
<td><pre>op1 = PM[Z]
Z = Z + 1</pre></td>
<td><pre>pc: increment
sreg: unchanged</pre></td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>Now, finally, we can describe a scheme for including data along
with our programs and using that data.  For instance, suppose we want
to make a program that prints 'Hello World!', we do the following: We
make the first instruction of the program an rjmp to the actual start
of the program.  After the first instruction, we include all the data
we want to use--in this case, the string 'Hello World!'.  Then we
start the actual program, and we can access the data by means of
labels when needed:

<code>rjmp prog_start
.asciz &quot;Hello World!&quot;
prog_start:
ldi r30, 255
out 26, r30
ldi r30,0
ldi r31,2
loop_start:
lpm r16,Z+
out 27, r16
cmp r16,0
brne loop_start</code>
</p>

</text></section>

</section>

</section>
